Guide to the Nott Family Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Nott Family Papers
1797-1944
RG 304
Yale University Divinity School Library
1.5
(4 boxes)
The Nott Family Papers document the life and work of three generations of family members. Eliphalet Nott (1773-1866) served as president of Union College for 62 years beginning in 1804. Eliphalet's brother Samuel Nott (1754-1852) was a Congregational minister in Franklin, Connecticut for 70 years. The bulk of the collection relates to Samuel's son, also named Samuel (1787-1869) who, with his wife Roxana Peck Nott, went to India as part of the first group of missionaries commissioned by the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions.
Nott, Eliphalet, 1773-1866
Nott, Samuel, 1788-1869
Nott, Samuel, 1754-1852
Biographical / Historical
Eliphalet Nott (1773-1866), a Presbyterian clergyman known as a gifted pulpit orator, served churches in New York state before becoming president of Union College in 1804, where he served for 62 years. Eliphalet's brother Samuel Nott (1754-1852) was a Congregational minister in Franklin, Connecticut for 70 years. During the course of his long ministry he instructed over 200 young men in his home, preparing some for college and some for theological training. His younger brother Eliphalet was one of the students he instructed.
Samuel Nott (1787-1869) was the son of Samuel (1750-1852). Roxana Peck (1785-1876) spent her childhood in Franklin, CT Before her marriage to Samuel (1787-1869) in 1812, she had taught school at various places in Connecticut and Maine. Shortly after their marriage, Roxana and Samuel went to India as part of the first group of missionaries commissioned by the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions. They were compelled to return to the United States in 1816 because of ill health, and were released from Board service at that time. For several years Samuel taught in New York City. In 1823 the family moved to Galway, NY, where he became pastor of a Presbyterian church there; and in 1829 he became pastor of the Congregational church in Wareham, Ma. Samuel returned to teaching in 1849; and the family moved to Hartford in 1866.
Samuel and Roxana Nott had seven children: Eliphalet, Gordon Hall (d.1903?), Harriet, John Wade (1822-1911), Samuel (1815-1899), Sarah Maria (1826-1910?),and William (1817-1890).Little is known about the lives of Eliphalet, Harriet, and Sarah Maria. Gordon Hall and Samuel (1815-1899) were civil engineers whose professional work was with various railway companies. William was a seaman; and John Wade was an Episcopal rector.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from Andover Newton Theological School, 2017.
Custodial History
Donated to Andover Newton Theological School by Roxana Vivian, granddaughter of Gordon Hall Nott.
Scope and Contents
This collection documents the life and work of three generations of the Nott family. Eliphalet Nott (1773-1866) served as president of Union College for 62 years beginning in 1804. Eliphalet's brother Samuel Nott (1754-1852) was a Congregational minister in Franklin, Connecticut for 70 years. The bulk of the collection relates to Samuel's son, also named Samuel (1787-1869) who, with his wife Roxana Peck Nott, went to India as part of the first group of missionaries commissioned by the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions. The lives and work of Samuel and Roxana's seven children are also documented.
The collection includes correspondence and memorabilia collected by Roxana Nott Vivian and Roxana H. Vivian, respectively daughter and granddaughter of Gordon Hall Nott. The material is arranged by generation, alphabetical order by given name within each generation.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into five series:
Series I. Papers of Eliphalet Nott (1773-1866).
Series II. Papers of Samuel Nott (1754-1852).
Series III. Papers of Papers of Roxana Peck Nott.
Series IV. Papers of Samuel Nott (1787-1869).
Series V. Papers of children of Roxana and Samuel Nott.
Clergy -- Connecticut; Missions -- India
- Papers of Eliphalet Nott (1773-1866), Series I
  - Correspondence
    - Letters from brother Samuel Nott (1754-1852), primarily written from Franklin, Connecticut, 1797–1835 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
  - Memorabilia
    - Horatio Potter, Address delivered at the Annual Commencement of Union College, June 23, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Eliphalet Nott: a memorial" [three addresses delivered at Ashford, Conn.], 1933 October 21 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Dixon Ryan Fox, "Dr. Eliphalet Nott (1773-1866) and the American spirit" (A Newcomen Address), 1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Perseventia vincit omnia nec non et in gloriam ducit"(Union College), 1858 March (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - George C. Chappell, "Eliphalet Nott: an address" [at the dedication of the Eliphalet Nott Memorial Highway], 1933 October 21 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Invitation to unveiling of marker of Eliphalet Nott Memorial Highway, 1933 October (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Reverend Eliphalet Nott Memorial dedication: programme", 1933 October 21 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Photograph of Mrs. Joel Nott and Margaret Cooper, No date (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "In memoriam: Mrs. Urania E. Nott", 1886? (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clippings
    - "A daily lesson in history: Rev. Eliphalet Nott, the college president who invented a stove", No date (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "Mother and sons", No date (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Untitled, on Hon. Charles Cooper Nott, son of Eliphalet, No date (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "Services tomorrow for Mrs. Sturges", No date (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "2 Liberty ships launched at South Portland yard", No date (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "In memory of Eliphalet Nott", 1904? (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - W. Scott, "Great American college presidents: Eliphalet Nott of Union College" ( The People >, March-May 1908) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "Letters from the people: 'The Everlasting Perkinses"', 1912 March 29 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Photograph of memorial marker ( Union Alumni Monthly ), 1933 November (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "News and comment: The Nott Highway" ( Union Alumni Monthly ), 1933 November (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "1934 sees how students of 1834 lived" (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Writings
    - Miscellaneous Works by Eliphalet Nott (Schenectady, 1810) (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Papers of Samuel Nott (1754-1852), Series II
  - Correspondence
    Scope and Contents
    The correspondence includes some letters addressed to Lucretia Nott, wife of Samuel (1754-1852)
    - From son Samuel, including from Calcutta and Bombay, 1810–1813 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - From son Samuel in Bombay, 1813–1815 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - From son Samuel in London and New York; from brother Eliphalet in Schenectady, 1816–1817 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - From daughter-in-law Roxana and son Samuel in New York; from brother Eliphalet in Schenectady, 1818–1820 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - To the Society Committee of Franklin Church; from son Samuel in New York, 1821–1822 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - To David Brainerd Spencer, David Putnam; from George M. Selden, 1825–1827 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - From son Samuel in Wareham; brother Eliphalet in Schenectady; Sherman Converse in New York, 1829–1831 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - From son Samuel in Wareham; grandson Samuel in Springfield, MA; to/from Levi Hart Godard, 1832–1835 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - From son Samuel in Wareham; to Levi Hart Godard and Charles Goddard, 1836–1838 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - From C.H.B. Lord in Adams, Ohio; from son Samuel and daughter-in-law Roxana in Wareham; to John W. Allen and Thomas Lord, 1839–1842 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - From son Samuel in Wareham; Timothy M. Cooley in Granville; A. Rankin in Chester, VT; to A. Rankin, 1843–1844 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - From son Samuel in Wareham; Royal R. Hinman in Hartford, 1845–1851 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Memorabilia
    - Six documents concerning land deed and legal transactions (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Account of Samuel Nott by Kingman Nott, 1851 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - E.W. Robinson, "Lines addressed to Rev. Samuel Nott D.D., at his house, on his 97th birth day [sic], Jan. 23d, 1851" (printed, no source) (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Bound volume: "The Celebration of the One Hundred and Fiftieth Anniversary of the Primitive Organization of the Congregational Church and Society in Franklin, Connecticut", 1869 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Papers of Roxana Peck Nott, Series III
  - Writings
    - Biblical lessons on Genesis written for her children, 1821-1822, no date (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Memoir: "A Little story: recollections from her earliest years of Mrs. Roxana Nott, written in her ninetieth year" (typewritten transcript, no date) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Memorabilia
    - Stories of 1806 eclipse retold; how it scared cows on Common" ( Boston Herald ), 1906? (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - How it seemed in the 1806 eclipse (Transcript, no date) (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Two letters to Roxana Vivian from Stacy R. Warburton regarding his research on RPN, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - [Roxana Vivian], "Recollections" (Roxana Nott's memoir with additions and annotations) (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Papers of Samuel Nott (1787-1869), Series IV
  - Correspondence
    - From father Samuel and sister Susan in Franklin, 1804–1809 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - From father Samuel in Franklin (including notes from mother Lucretia and sister Lucretia), 1810 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - From father Samuel in Franklin (including notes from mother and siblings); from George Burden, Levi Hart, Gordon Hall, 1811 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - From Adoniram Judson in Andover; Charles B. King in Hartford; Robert Ralston in Philadelphia, 1812 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - From Eleazer Lord in Andover; to unidentified person, written from Calcutta, 1812 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - From parents and siblings; from Adoniram Judson in Port Louis; from [Samuel Newell] and J.W. [Sheser?] in Calcutta, 1813 January - May (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - From Samuel Newell in Colombo; father Samuel in Franklin (includes letter to Roxana from Samuel's sister Lucretia); Margaret Cleveland in Norwich (includes letter from [W. & M.?] Cleveland), 1813 July - September (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - From Roxana in Bombay; parents and siblings in Franklin; Jonathan Hyde in Liverpool; [Roxana] to Samuel Newell from Bombay, 1813 October - November (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - To Samuel Worcester; from Gordon Hall and Samuel Newell; Jonathan Mason; parents, 1814–1815 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - From Jeremiah Everts; [W.S. __]; Samuel Newell; Samuel Worcester; Eliphalet Nott; Eleazar Lord; J. Hunter; Miron Winslow, 1816 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - From Eleazer Lord; David Parker; Samuel Newell; Samuel Worcester; [Charles B.?] King; Robert Ralston; Daniel C. Banks; Gordon Hall and Samuel Newell; E.D. Griffin; Jeremiah Evarts; Eliphalet Nott; Samuel Worcester; Eleazer Lord; [James Kent?], 1817 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - From [James Kent?]; [Rensselaer Havens?]; Roxana and father Samuel in Franklin; Samuel Newell in Bombay, 1818 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - From parents, siblings, and Roxana in Franklin; James M. Winchellin Boston; Adoniram Judson in Rangoon; Krishnabhat Bedekar Vaidya (in Marathi? with English translation), 1819–1820 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - From Eliphalet Nott in Schenectady; Gordon Hall in Calcutta; father Samuel and sister Lucretia in Franklin; Henry Hill in Boston, 1823 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - From Eliza [Bruen?] in Boston; Forbes & Co. in Bombay (includes copies of letters to Messrs. Percher & Co., London, June 3, 1815, and Messrs. Inglis, Forbes & Co., London, Mar. 27, 1824); Benjamin Allen in Hyde Park, NY; Roxana in Galway, NY; Jeremiah Evarts in Boston; Gordon Hall in Bombay; Inglis Forbes & Co. in London, 1824–1825 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - From Jeremiah Evarts in Boston; Leonard Woods in Andover; Inglis Forbes & Co. in London (2 copies); father Samuel in Franklin; Margaret Hall in West Granville; Eliza Converse (aunt) in New Haven (includes letter from sister Eliza), 1826 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - From father Samuel in Franklin; Luther Rice in Washington, D.C. (circular letter with handwritten note); M. Winslow in [Oodooville?]; J. West in New York, 1827–1828 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - From Isaac Fobes in Wareham; Samuel Whittelsey in Utica; J. Hanes in Hartford; Caleb J. Tenney in Wethersfield, CT; father Samuel; Eliphalet Nott, 1829 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - From Selah Otis in Galway (includes letter from Caroline Otis), 1830 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - From son Samuel, 1833 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - From son Samuel, 1834-1835 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - From son Samuel, 1837 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - From sons Samuel and Eliphalet; from father Samuel, 1838–1842 (Box 2, Folder 9-12)
    - From son Samuel and father Samuel; from L. Ashburner; G.W. Blagden; M.B. Sedgwick; Gordon H. Nott; W.C. Woodbridge, 1843–1844 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - From son Samuel and father Samuel; from S. Holmes; Thomas Williams, 1845–1846 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - From son Samuel and father Samuel; from Lucretia Hyde (niece); Rufus Rood, 1847–1850 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - From Samuel Nott Hyde (nephew); James Smith; Eliphalet Nott; Eli Hyde; E. Bigelow; son Samuel, 1852–1855 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Including from son Samuel; S. Holmes, 1856–1860 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - From son Samuel, 1861–1865 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - From Gordon Hall; L. Asburner, Undated; ca. 1816-1824 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Memorabilia
    - Photographs of Samuel, his ordination, and Wareham church, No date (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Noble W. Everett, "Historical Paper, No. 10: Rev. Samuel Nott, Jr." (no source, no date) (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - "The Haystack Meeting and its Outcome", reprinted from In Lands Afar, No date (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Letter to Samuel from Chief Justice Taney, Aug. 19, 1857, printed with introduction by Massachusetts Historical Society, March 1873 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - "The Door Opened: A Missionary Story" [pamphlet], May 1899, reprinted from Religious Herald, February 1892 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - "The Haystack Centennial" ( Springfield Republican, July 29, 1906) (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - "Memorial boulder on Andover Hill," reprinted from Andover Townsman, July 29, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Letter to Roxana Vivian from C.C. Carpenter, Oct. 5, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - "Proceedings at the unveiling of the monument to commemorate the organization of the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions" [pamphlet] Oct. 12, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - American Board Centennial, 1910: Pilgrimage to Andover: itinerary and dedication service, October 12, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Letter to Roxana Vivian from C.C. Carpenter, October 13, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - "Andover pilgrimage" ( Phillips Bulletin, January 1911) (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - [Announcement of anniversary ordinations, February 6, 1912], Tabernacle Church (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - [Invitation to anniversary ordinations, with RSVP request and ticket], January 15, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - "Centenary of the ordination of the first missionaries ..." - order of worship and photographs] Tabernacle Church, February 6, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Five new missionaries ordained at Tabernacle ( Salem Evening News, February 7, 1912) (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Commemorations of centennial of Samuel Nott, Jr. sailing as missionary, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Memoir: "In memoriam Rev. Samuel Nott, 1788-1869." Manuscript dated 12/19/95, copied and annotated by son Samuel from Samuel, Jr.'s manuscript (Box 2, Folder 24-27)
    - Continuation of "In memoriam Rev. Samuel Nott, 1788-1869." Manuscript dated 12/19/95, copied and annotated by son Samuel from Samuel, Jr.'s manuscript (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - "Memoirs of Harriet Newell", 1815 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Writings
    - Writings by Samuel Nott, Jun.: "Memorial of Sarah Salwa, an African girl, who died in the New-York Hospital, Sept. 1822, about 18 years of age" in The Christian Herald; Sermons for Children (1828); The Telescope: or Sacred Views of Things Past, Present, and to Come (1832), 1823-1832 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Papers of Children of Roxana and Samuel Nott, Series V
  - Eliphalet Nott
    - Journal, 1835 July 30 - 1838 August 21 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Loose pages from journal, March -October [1850] and envelope with notes by [R. Vivian] (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Obituary of Eliphalet 2 ( Chicago Tribune, no date) (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Obituary of Richard Hartley Nott (Eliphalet's son) ( Biddeford Daily Journal, January 23, 1915) (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - List of "papers destroyed," Hartley Nott estate; with notes on H. Nott (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Gordon Hall Nott
    - Correspondence, including from A. Webster, George Curtis Treadwell, Abram S. Hewitt, Samuel Babcock; to/from Theodore Roosevelt, 1868, 1899, 1900, 1903 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Memorabilia, including articles by Gordon Hall Nott regarding Chicago sewage system; obituary, 1886–1903 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Harriet Nott
    - Notebook, including biblical texts arranged by topic (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - John Wade Nott
    - Memorabilia including Confirmation certificate, Sept. 10, 1848, Certificate of completion, General Theological Seminary, June 26, 1851, Certificate of ordination as deacon, Sept. 23, 1851; Shares in Waukulla Mining Co., certificates 23, 25, 26, 28; Oct. 22, 1860, 1848–1860 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Article and sermon by J. W. Nott, 1882–1885 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Obituary and tributes to J. W. Nott, 1911 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Will and legal documents, 1904–1912 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Photographs of Nott, rectory and church, clergy, No date (Box 3, Folder 10-11)
  - Samuel Nott (1815-1899)
    - Notebook; includes autobiographical notes made 1863-1890 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, including to/from parents and siblings; from A. Huntington, Robert E. Winthrop, A. C. Thompson, DeWitt S. Clark, George E. Gray, S. E. Tinkham, 1856-1895 (Box 3, Folder 13-14)
    - Obituary and tributes to Samuel (1815-1899), 1899–1903 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Photographs of Samuel
  - Sarah Maria Nott
    - "A little story: recollections from her earliest years of Mrs. Roxana Nott," copied and annotated by Sarah Nott (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Obituary, will, account of estate of Sarah, 1904–1910 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Photograph of Sarah M. Nott, 1902 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Drawing of Washington's headquarters, Newburgh, N.Y., by Sarah M. Nott (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - William Nott
    - Account of clipper ship "Don Quixote", unidentified hand;Reference for William Nott from G.B. _of ship "Illinois", No date (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Obituary and memorial to William, 1890 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Photograph of wife Mary Nye Nott, No date (Box 3, Folder 18)